Bibliographic references Referências bibliográficas Referencias bibliográficas

Lingüística e Historia da LinguaLinguística e História da Língua Linguistics and Historical Linguistics
Lírica galego-portuguesaGalician-Portuguese Medieval Poetry
Crítica textual e Humanidades DixitaisCrítica textual e Humanidades DigitaisTextual scholarship and Digital Humanities

Lingüística e Historia da LinguaLinguística e História da Língua Linguistics and Historical Linguistics

Alarcos Llorach, E. (2012), Fonología española, 4ath ed, Gredos, Madrid [1ast ed. 1950].

Álvarez, R. (1994), “As formas de dativo e a expresión do número en galego medieval: lle / lles, llo / llelo”, Verba 21: 133–166.

Álvarez, R. (2004), “A variación nosco : connosco : con nós en galego medieval”, Verba 31: 43–73.

Álvarez, R. (2007), “Variación dialectal no período de emerxencia”, in A. I. Boullón Agrelo (ed.), Na nosa lyngoage galega: a emerxencia do galego como lingua escrita na Idade Media, Consello da Cultura Galega-Instituto da Lingua Galega, Santiago de Compostela, 373–397.

Álvarez, R. & Xove Ferreiro, X. (1999), “Lingua e variación dialectal na Crónica Xeral Galega”, in D. Kremer (ed.), Homenaxe a Ramón Lorenzo, Vol. 1, Galaxia, Vigo, 29–58.

Brea, M. (1985), “Las preposiciones, del latín a las lenguas románicas”, Verba 12: 147–182.

Brea, M. (1991), “La partícula gallego-portuguesa ar/er”, in P. Pereira (ed.), Homenaje a Alonso Zamora Vicente, Castalia, Madrid, 45–57.

Cappelli, A. (ed.) (1995), Dizionario di abbreviature latine ed italiane, 6ath ed, Ulrico Hoepli, Milano [1ast ed. 1912].

Carvalho, M. J. (2001), “Variação morfossintáctica no português medieval: as formas femininas dos pronomes possessivos”, Revista Portuguesa de Filologia 21: 181–208.

Corominas, J. & Pascual, J. A. (1980a), s.v. “lacerar”, in Diccionario crítico etimológico castellano e hispánico, Vol. III, Gredos, Madrid, 548–550.

Corominas, J. & Pascual, J. A. (1980b), s.v. “más”, in Diccionario crítico etimológico castellano e hispánico, Vol. III, Gredos, Madrid, 867–868.

Costas González, X. H. (1999), “As voltas co enxordecemento das sibilantes sonoras no galego medieval”, in A. C. M. Lopes & C. Martins (eds.), Actas do XIV Encontro nacional da Associação Portuguesa de Linguística, Vol. I, Associação Portuguesa de Linguística, Braga, 433–445.

Ferreiro, M. (1999), Gramática histórica galega: Fonética e morfoxintaxe, 4ath ed, Edicións Laiovento.

Galmés de Fuentes, A. (1962), Las Sibilantes en la Romania, Gredos, Madrid.

Gonçalves, M. F. M. (2002), “Morfologia verbal do galego-português: pretéritos fortes em vias de desaparecimento”, in B. F. Head (ed.), História da língua e história da gramática : actas do Encontro, Universidade do Minho, Centro de Estudos Humanísticos, Braga, 103–111.

Hermida Gulías, C. (1994), “O artigo co posesivo adxacente no galego medieval. Unha hipótese”, in R. Lorenzo (ed.), Actas del XIX Congreso Internacional de Lingüística e Filoloxía Románicas, Vol. VI, Fundación Pedro Barrié de la Maza, Conde de Fenosa, A Coruña, 297–308.

Huber, J. (1933), Altportugiesisches Elementarbuch, Carl Winters, Heidelberg.

Jakobson, R. (1971), Selected Writings: Phonological studies, Mouton, The Hague.

Jenset, G. B. & McGillivray, B. (2017), Quantitative Historical Linguistics: A Corpus Framework, Oxford Studies in Diachronic and Historical Linguistics, Oxford University Press, Oxford, New York.

Larson, P. (2018), La lingua delle cantigas. Grammatica del galego-portoghese, Carocci editore, Roma.

Lausberg, H. (1985), Lingüística románica, Gredos, Madrid [3ard reimp., ed. original alemã 1956].

Lloyd, P. M. (1987), From Latin to Spanish, Vol. I, American Philosophical Society, Philadelphia.

Lorenzo, R. (1987), “Algunhas consideracións sobre a História do Galego-Português de Clarinda de Azevedo Maia”, Verba 14: 441–488.

Lorenzo, R. (1995), “Algúns datos sobre a evolución das sibilantes medievais”, in C. Cunha Pereira, P. R. Dias Pereira & C. Cunha (eds.), Miscelânea de estudos lingüísticos, filológicos e literários in memoriam Celso Cunha, Nova Fronteira, Rio de Janeiro, 231–237.

Lorenzo, R. (2007), “Os notarios e a lingua nos comezos da escrita documental galega”, in A. I. Boullón Agrelo (ed.), Na nosa lyngoage galega: a emerxencia do galego como lingua escrita na Idade Media, Consello da Cultura Galega-Instituto da Lingua Galega, Santiago de Compostela, 313–372.

Lorenzo, R. (ed.) (1985), Crónica troiana, Fundación Pedro Barrié de la Maza, A Coruña.

Machado, J. P. (1977), s.v. “lazeiro”, in Dicionário etimológico da língua portuguesa: com a mais antiga documentaçaã escrita e conhecida de muitos dos vocábulos estudados, 3ard ed, Vol. III, Livros Horizonte, Lisboa, 396.

Maia, C. de Azevedo (1986), História do galego-português: estado linguistico da Galiza e do Noroeste de Portugal desde o século XIII ao século XVI, Fundação Calouste Gulbenkian / Junta Nacional de Investigaçao Científica e Tecnológica, Lisboa.

Malkiel, Y. (1971), “Derivational Transparency as an Occasional Co-determinant of Sound Change: A New Causal Ingredient in the Distribution of -ç- and -z- in Ancient Hispano-Romance”, Romance philology 25: 1–52.

Malkiel, Y. (1988), “A cluster of (old) Portuguese derivational suffixes: -ece, -ice, -ez(a), viewed in relation to their spanish counterparts”, Bulletin of Hispanic Studies 65: 1–19.

Marcerano, V. (2018), La lingua dei trobadores, Viella, Roma [No prelo].

Mariño Paz, R. (2002), “A desnasalización vocálica no galego medieval”, Verba 29: 71–118.

Mariño Paz, R. (2005), “Cronoloxía da extinción dos lexemas criv- / crev e siv- / sev- dos temas de perfecto dos verbos cre(e)r e se(e)r no galego medieval”, in A. I. Boullón Agrelo, X. L. Couceiro & F. Fernández Rei (eds.), As tebras alumeadas: Estudos filolóxicos ofrecidos en homenaxe a Ramón Lorenzo, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 191–204.

Mariño Paz, R. (2009), “A vogal /i/ en posición átona final de palabra no galego medieval”, Revista de Filología Románica 26: 71–98.

Mariño Paz, R. (2017), Fonética e fonoloxía históricas da lingua galega, Edicións Xerais de Galicia, Vigo.

Monteagudo, H. (2008), Letras primeiras: o Foral de Caldelas, a emerxencia da escrita en galego e os primordios da lírica trobadoresca, Fundación Pedro Barrié de la Maza, A Coruña.

Neto, S. da Silva (1979), História da língua portuguesa, 3ard ed, Presença, Rio de Janeiro.

Nunes, J. J. (1975), Compêndio de gramática histórica portuguesa. Fonética e morfologia, 8a ed, Livraria Clássica Editora, Lisboa [1ast ed. 1919].

Penny, R. J. (2004), Variación y cambio en español, Gredos, Madrid.

Penny, R. J. (2010), Gramática histórica del español, Ariel Lingüística, 2and ed, Ariel, Barcelona.

Pichel Gotérrez, R. (2010), “Contribución a braquigrafía do galego medieval. Procedementos abreviativos e transcendencia escriptolingüística”, in XXXIX Simposio Internacional de la Sociedad Española de Lingúística, Unidixital, Santiago de Compostela.

Pichel Gotérrez, R. (2012), “A representación gráfica da nasalidade vocálica e do trazo palatal no galego antigo e o seu tratamento editorial”, Estudos de lingüística galega 4: 87–106.

Riiho, T. (1979), Por y para: estudio sobre los orígenes y la evolución de una oposición prepositiva iberorrománica, Academic bookstore.

Rodríguez Guerra, A. (2001), “Conxuncións e locucións temporais en galego medieval”, Verba 28: 207–258.

Rohlfs, G. (1966), Grammatica storica della lingua italiana e dei suoi dialetti. Fonetica, Einaudi, Torino.

Rubio, L. & González Rolán, T. (1990), Nueva gramática latina, 3ard ed, Coloquio Editorial, Madrid.

Santamarina, A. (1974a), “Contribución pra un estudio das partículas comparativas que = ca e como = coma en galego”, Verba 1: 16–30.

Santamarina, A. (1974b), El verbo gallego: estudio basado en el habla del Valle del Suarna, Universidad de Santiago de Compostela, Secretariado de Publicaciones, Santiago de Compostela.

Santamarina, A. (1975), “El adverbio gallego: estudio basado en el habla del valle del Suarna”, Verba 2: 59–106.

Silva Domínguez, C. (2002), “A perda da serie reducida feminina do posesivo en textos notariais galegos e portugueses da época medieval: cronoloxía e pautas no proceso de difusión da innovación”, Verba 29: 153–188.

Soto Andión, X. (2004), “Aproximación histórica ás formas verbais dicir, querer e facer”, in R. Álvarez, F. Fernández Rei & A. Santamarina (eds.), A Lingua Galega: historia e actualidade: Actas do I Congreso Internacional (Santiago de Compostela, 16-20 de setembro de 1996), Vol. III, Consello da Cultura Galega / Instituto da Lingua Galega, Santiago de Compostela, 299–315.

Souto Cabo, J. A. (2008a), Documentos galego-portugueses dos séculos XII e XIII, Universidade da Coruña, A Coruña.

Tekavčić, P. (1972), Grammatica storica dell'italiano: Fonematica, Il mulino.

Teyssier, P. (1994), História da língua portuguesa, 6a ed, Sá da Costa, Lisboa [1ast ed. francesa 1980].

Varela Barreiro, F. X. (ed.) (2004), Tesouro Medieval Informatizado da Lingua Galega, Instituto da Lingua Galega, Santiago de Compostela [= TMILGA]. [Link].

Verdelho, E. (2004), “Filologia, Linguística e Informática: trabalhos em tempo de mudança”, in A. M. Brito, O. Figueiredo & A. Barros (eds.), Linguística Histórica e História da Língua Portuguesa (Actas do Encontro de Homenagem a Maria Helena de Paiva), Faculdade de Letras, Porto, 397–411.

Vicente Llavata, S. (2013), “Historia de la lengua, lingüística de corpus y cambio lingüístico: en torno a la irrupción de las nuevas tecnologías en la investigación histórica del español”, Analecta Malacitana 36(1-2): 393–421.

Williams, E. B. (1962), From Latin to Portuguese. Historical phonology and morphology of the Portuguese language, 2and ed, University of Pennsylvania Press, Philadelphia [1ast ed. 1938].

Zufferey, F. (1987), Recherches linguistiques sur les chansonniers provençaux, Droz, Genève.

↑

Lírica galego-portuguesaGalician-Portuguese Medieval Poetry

Arbor Aldea, M. (2001), O cancioneiro de Afonso Sanchez. Edición e estudio, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela.

Arbor Aldea, M. (2005), “Os estudos sobre o Cancioneiro da Ajuda: un estado da cuestión”, in M. Brea (ed.), Carolina Michaëlis e o Cancioneiro da Ajuda, hoxe, Xunta de Galicia, Dirección Xeral de Política Lingüística / Centro Ramón Piñeiro para a Investigación en Humanidades, Santiago de Compostela, 45–120.

Arbor Aldea, M. (2008), Cancioneiro da Ajuda, Xunta de Galicia, Santiago de Compostela.

Arbor Aldea, M. (2009a), “Escribir nas marxes, completar o texto: as notas ós versos do Cancioneiro da Ajuda”, in M. Brea (ed.), “Pola melhor dona de quantas fez nostro Senhor”: homenaxe á profesora Giulia Lanciani, Xunta de Galicia / Centro Ramón Piñeiro para a Investigación en Humanidades, Santiago de Compostela, 49–72.

Arbor Aldea, M. (2009b), “Un códice de historia material compleja: El Cancioneiro da Ajuda”, Revista Medieval 21: 77–124.

Arbor Aldea, M. (2010), “Lais de Bretanha galego-portugueses e tradición manuscrita: as relacións entre B e L”, in M. Iliescu, H. Siller-Runggaldier & P. Danler (eds.), Actes du XXVme Congrès International de Linguistique et de Philologie Romanes (Innsbruck 2007), Vol. VI, De Gruyter, Berlin / New York, 11–20.

Arbor Aldea, M. (2012a), “Mais bisílabo? Notas á marxe do Cancioneiro da Ajuda”, in P. Lorenzo Gradín & S. Marcerano (eds.), El texto medieval: de la edición a la interpretación, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 157–192.

Arbor Aldea, M. (2012b), “A fronte a BV: res metrica e varia lectio (I)”, in N. Fernández Rodríguez & M. Ferreiro (eds.), Literatura medieval y renacentista en España: Líneas y pautas, SEMYR, Salamanca, 363–376.

Arbor Aldea, M. (2012c), A fronte a BV: res metrica e varia lectio (II), in A. Martínez Pérez e A. L. Baquero Escudero (eds.), Estudios de literatura medieval: 25 años de la Asociación Hispánica de Literatura Medieval, Universidad de Murcia, Servicio de Publicaciones, Murcia, 159–170.

Arbor Aldea, M. (2016a), Cancioneiro da Ajuda. Transcrición e notas, Virtual Center for the Study of Galician-Portuguese Lyric, DC Washington. [Link].

Arbor Aldea, M. (2016b), “Andamos fazendo dança, cantando nosas bailadas. Notas críticas a O Maroot haja mal grado (B2, L2)”, in E. Corral Díaz, E. Fidalgo Francisco e P. Lorenzo Gradín (eds.), Cantares de amigos. Estudos en homenaxe a Mercedes Brea, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 85–95.

Arbor Aldea, M., Canettieri, P. & Pulsoni, C. (2004), “Le forme metriche del Cancioneiro da Ajuda”, in O Cancioneiro da Ajuda cen anos despois: actas do Congreso realizado pola Dirección Xeral de Promoción Cultural en Santiago de Compostela e na Illa de San Simón os días 25-28 de maio de 2004, Consellería de Cultura, Comunicación Social e Turismo, Santiago de Compostela, 145–175.

Arbor Aldea, M. & Ciaralli, A. (2018), “Il Pergamiño Vindel: stato codicologico e paleografico”, in B. Arias Freixedo & A. Rodríguez Guerra (eds.), The Vindel Parchment and Martin Codax: The Golden Age of the Medieval Galician Poetry, John Benjamins Publishing, Chicago, 138–165.

Arbor Aldea, M. & Pulsoni, C. (2004), “Il Cancioneiro da Ajuda prima di Carolina Michaëlis (1904)”, Critica del testo, 7(2): 721–789.

Arbor Aldea, M. & Varela Barreiro, F. X. (2008), “O uso dos signos gráficos “i” e “y” como segundo elemento de diptongo decrecente: a evidencia de dúas mans na copia do Cancionerio da Ajuda”, in M. Brea, F. Fernández Rei & X. L. Regueira Fernández (eds.), Cada palabra pesaba, cada palabra medía: homenaxe a Antón Santamarina, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 419–442.

Arbor Aldea, M. (ed.) (2016c), Pergamino Vindel, M. Moleiro, Barcelona.

Arbor Aldea, M., Rodríguez Guerra, A. & Varela Barreiro, F. X. (2014), “As abreviaturas no Cancioneiro da Ajuda: tipos, valores e distribución”, Revista galega de filoloxía 15: 11–51.

Bermúdez Sabel, H. (2016), “Variación gráfica na lírica profana galego-portuguesa: T vs. BV”, in E. Corral Díaz, E. Fidalgo Francisco & P. Lorenzo Gradín (eds.), Cantares de amigos. Estudos en homenaxe a Mercedes Brea, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 93–99.

Bertolucci Pizzorusso, V. (1963), Le Poesie di Martin di Soares, Libreria Antiguaria Palmaverde, Bologna.

Brea, M. (1997), “Las anotaciones de Angelo Colocci en el Cancionero de la Biblioteca Vaticana”, Revista de Filología Románica 14: 515–519.

Brea, M. (ed.) (1996), Lírica profana galego-portuguesa: corpus completo das cantigas medievais, con un estudio biográfico, análise retórica e bibliografía específica, Centro de Investigacións Lingüísticas e Literarias Ramón Piñero, Santiago de Compostela.

Ciaralli, A. (2016), “Descripción paleográfica”, in M. Arbor Aldea (ed.), Pergamino Vindel, M. Moleiro, Barcelona, 41–55.

Cohen, R. (2003), 500 cantigas d'amigo, Campo das Letras, Porto.

Coiradas Martínez, I. (2013), A Mediación na lírica galego-portuguesa: edición e anotación das rúbricas explicativas, Tese de doutoramento inédita, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Santiago de Compostela.

Cunha, C. Ferreira da (1961), Estudos de poética trovadoresca. Versificação e ecdótica, Instituto Nacional do Livro, Rio de Janeiro.

D’Heur, J.-M. (1974), “Sur la tradition manuscrite des chansonniers galiciens-portugais. Contribution à la Bibliographie Générale et au Corpus des troubadours”, Arquivos do Centro Cultural Português 8: 3–43.

D’Heur, J.-M. (1984), “Sur la généalogie des chansonniers portugais d'Ange Colocci”, Boletim de filologia 29(2): 23–34.

Fernández Guiadanes, A. (2010), “Particularidades gráficas e de impaxinación do folio 79r do Cancioneiro da Ajuda: o seu copista é ¿un copista-corrector?”, in M. Arbor Aldea & A. Fernández Guiadanes (eds.), Estudos de edición crítica e lírica galego-portuguesa, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 163–194.

Fernández Guiadanes, A. (2011), “Uso y funciones de la plica en el Cancionero da Ajuda: identificación del usus scribendi de los copistas”, in M. Salamanca López (ed.), La materialidad escrita: nuevos enfoques para su interpretación, Instituto de Estudios para la Paz y la Cooperación, Oviedo, 49–107.

Fernández Guiadanes, A. (2012), “Da articulación textual nos testemuños da lírica profana galego-portuguesa”, Revista de Cancioneros Impresos y Manuscritos (1): 105–160 [Link].

Fernández Guiadanes, A. (2016), “Dúas notas sobre a transmisión manuscrita da lírica galego-portuguesa”, in E. Corral Díaz, E. Fidalgo Francisco & P. Lorenzo Gradín (eds.), Cantares de amigos: estudos en homenaxe a Mercedes Brea, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 369–375.

Fernández Guiadanes, A. & Pérez Barcala, G. (2009), “Notas sobre o texto e a copia dalgunhas cantigas galego-portuguesas: una errata divisione dei versi”, in M. Brea (ed.), “Pola melhor dona de quantas fez nostro Senhor”: homenaxe á profesora Giulia Lanciani, Xunta de Galicia / Centro Ramón Piñeiro para a Investigación en Humanidades, Santiago de Compostela, 189–223.

Fernández Guiadanes, A. & Río Riande, M. G. del (2010), “Función dos signos gráficos nos testemuños musicados contemporáneos á época de produción trobadoresca profana en galego-portugués (I): o Pergamiño Sharrer e o Pergamiño Vindel”, Ars Metrica 10 [Link].

Ferrari, A. (1979), “Formazione e struttura del canzoniere portoghese della Biblioteca Nazionale di Lisbona (cod. 10991: Colocci-Brancuti). Premesse codicologiche alla critica del testo (Materiali e note problematiche)”, Arquivos do Centro Cultural Português XIV: 27–142.

Ferrari, A. (1993a), s.v. “Cancioneiro da Biblioteca Nacional (Colocci-Brancuti)”, in G. Lanciani & G. Tavani (eds.), Dicionário da literatura medieval galega e portuguesa, Caminho, Lisboa, 119–122.

Ferrari, A. (1993b), s.v. ”Cancioneiro da Biblioteca Vaticana”, in G. Lanciani & G. Tavani (eds.), Dicionário da literatura medieval galega e portuguesa, Caminho, Lisboa, 123–126.

Ferreira, M. P. (1986), O som de Martin Codax. Sobre a dimensão musical da lírica galego- portuguesa (séculos XII-XIV), Unisys, Lisboa.

Ferreira, M. Pedro (2004), “O rasto da música no Cancioneiro da Ajuda”, in O Cancioneiro da Ajuda cen anos despois: actas do Congreso realizado pola Dirección Xeral de Promoción Cultural en Santiago de Compostela e na Illa de San Simón os días 25-28 de maio de 2004, Consellería de Cultura, Comunicación Social e Turismo, Santiago de Compostela, 185–210.

Ferreira, M. Pedro (2005), Cantus coronatus - Sete cantigas d’El-Rei Dom Dinis, Reichenberger, Kassel.

Ferreiro, M. (2008a), “Edición e historia da lingua: sobre a representación da nasalidade no trobadorismo profano galego-portugués e as formas “irmana” e afíns”, in M. Ferreiro, C. P. Martínez Pereiro & L. Tato Fontaíña (eds.), A edición da poesía trobadoresca en Galiza, Baía, A Coruña, 77–96.

Ferreiro, M. (2008b), “A forma verbal “éste” na lírica profana galego-portuguesa”, Revista Galega de Filoloxía 9: 57–78.

Ferreiro, M. (2010), “Os hapax como problema e como solución. Sobre a cantiga 493/18,11 [B 495/V 78] de Afonso X”, in M. Arbor Aldea & A. Fernández Guiadanes (eds.), Estudos de edición crítica e lírica galego-portuguesa, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 239–262.

Ferreiro, M. (2012a), “Do manuscrito á edición: consideracións sobre a segmentación textual na poesía profana galego-portuguesa”, in P. Lorenzo Gradín & S. Marcenaro (eds.), El texto medieval: de la edición a la interpretación, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 135–157.

Ferreiro, M. (2012b), “Erros dos copistas, lapsos dos editores: o pronome “che” e a cantiga B 1584 - V 1116 de Afonso Eanes do Coton”, in N. Fernández Rodríguez, M. Fernández Ferreiro & M. Ferreiro (eds.), Literatura medieval y renacentista en España: líneas y pautas, SEMYR, Salamanca, 545–561.

Ferreiro, M. (2012c), “Sobre a partícula “ca” no corpus da lírica profana galego-portuguesa: integridade formal vs. elisión”, in P. Pretov, R. López-Iglésias Samartim & E. J. Torres Feijó (eds.), Avanços em Ciências da Linguagem, Através-Associação Internacional de Lusitanistas, Santiago de Compostela-Faro, 391–410.

Ferreiro, M. (2013), “Sobre a posibilidade de elisión vocálica na conxunción “se” na poesía profana galego-portuguesa”, Verba 40: 453–470 [Link].

Ferreiro, M. (2014a), “Elementos para unha revisión textual das cantigas trobadorescas: sobre a segmentación de ‘o’ e ‘a’”, Estudos de Lingüística Galega 6: 81–115 [Link].

Ferreiro, M. (2014b), “Glosario da poesía medieval profana galego-portuguesa”. ISSN 2386-8309 [data da última revisão: 25/04/2017] [Link].

Ferreiro, M. (2014c), “Lección manuscrita e crítica do texto: en torno á segmentación das cadeas gráficas na poesía profana galego-portuguesa”, Revista de literatura medieval 26: 163–190 [Link].

Ferreiro, M. (2015), “Edición crítica e léxico: sobre algunhas cuestións de vocabulario na poesía profana galego-portuguesa”, in R. Mariño Paz & F. X. Varela Barreiro (eds.), Linguistica histórica e edición de textos galegos medievais, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 259–275.

Ferreiro, M. (2016a), “A forma “mais” na lírica profana galego-portuguesa: variación lingüística e estatus métrico”, Verba 43: 361–383 [Link].

Ferreiro, M. (2016b), “Materiais para unha revisión crítica da segmentación de é no texto das cantigas profanas galego-portuguesas”, in X. M. Sánchez Rei & M. A. Marques (eds.), As ciências da linguagem no espaço galego-português. Diversidade e convergência, Universidade do Minho, Minho, 39–64.

Ferreiro, M. (2016c), “Notas sobre variación lingüística dalgunhas formas verbais de pretérito nas cantigas galego-portuguesas (aver, fazer, põer, querer)”, in A. Rodríguez Guerra (ed.), Lingüística histórica e dialectoloxía: coordenadas do cambio lingüístico, 119–137.

Ferreiro, M. (2016d), “Unha variación inexistente nas cantigas profanas galego-portuguesas: as formas perdon-pardon”, Madrygal 19: 51–59.

Ferreiro, M. (2018), “Universo Cantigas. Edición crítica da poesía medieval galego-portuguesa”. ISSN 2605-1273 [data da última revisão: 28/08/2018] [Link].

Gonçalves, E. (1976), “La tavola colocciana: Autori portoghesi”, Arquivos do Centro Cultural Português X: 387–448.

Gonçalves, E. (1991), “Sur la lyrique galego-portugaise. Phénoménologie de la constitution des chansonniers ordonnés par genres”, in M. Tyssen (ed.), Lyrique romane médiévale: la tradition des chansonniers : actes du colloque de Liège, 1989, Université, Liège, 447–467.

Gonçalves, E. (1993), s.v. “Tradição manuscrita da poesia lírica”, in G. Lanciani & G. Tavani (eds.), Dicionário da literatura medieval galega e portuguesa, Caminho, Lisboa, 627–632.

Gonçalves, E. (1994), “O sistema das rubricas atributivas e explicativas nos cancioneiros trovadorescos galego-portuguese”, in R. Lorenzo (ed.), Actas do XIX Congreso Internacional de Lingüística e Filoloxía Románicas. Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, 1989 Sección IX. Filoloxía medieval e renacentista, Fundación Pedro Barrié de la Maza, Conde de Fenosa, A Coruña, 979–990.

Gonçalves, E. (2007), “Sobre a tradição manuscrita da lírica galego-portuguesa: conjecturas e contrariedades”, eHumanista: Journal of Iberian Studies (8): 1–27.

González Martínez, D. (2012), O cancioneiro de Fernan Fernandez Cogominho. Edición e estudo, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Cientifico, Santiago de Compostela.

Gutiérrez García, S. (2007), “La lírica gallego-portuguesa en los procesos de hegemonización y canonización de la literatura gallega”, Anuario de Estudios Medievales (AEM) 37(1): 245–265.

Lagares, X. C. (2000), E por esto fez este cantar: Sobre as rubricas explicativas dos cancioneiros profanos galego-portugueses, Laiovento, Santiago de Compostela.

Lagares, X. C. (2006), “Uma aproximação à “língua” das cantigas galego-portuguesas”, Revista galega de filoloxía 7: 95–116.

Lapa, M. R. (ed.) (1965), Cantigas d’escarnho e de mal dizer dos cancioneiros medievais galego-portugueses, Galaxia, Vigo.

Lattès, S. (1931), “Recherches sur la bibliothèque d'Angelo Colocci”, Mélanges d'archéol. et d'histoire XLVIII: 308–344.

Lopes, G. Videira e Ferreira, M. Pedro (eds.) (2016), Do canto à escrita: novas questões em torno da lírica galego-portuguesa: nos cem anos do pergaminho Vindel, IEM - Instituto de Estudos Medievais / CESEM - Centro de Estudos de Sociologia e Estética Musical, Lisboa.

Lopes, G. Videira, Ferreira, M. Pedro et al. (2011), Cantigas Medievais Galego Portuguesas [base de dados online], Instituto de Estudos Medievais, FCSH/NOVA, Lisboa [Link].

López Martínez, M. S. & Moscoso Mato, E. (2007), “Morfoloxía do Cancioneiro da Ajuda”, in A. I. Boullón Agrelo (ed.), Na nosa lyngoage galega: a emerxencia do galego como lingua escrita na Idade Media, Instituto da Lingua Galega, Santiago de Compostela, 557–578.

Lorenzo Gradín, P. (2000), “Trovadores, cronología y “razós” en los cancioneros gallego-portugueses”, in M. Freixas & S. Iriso (eds.), Actas del VIII Congreso Internacional de la Asociación Hispánica de Literatura Medieval. Santander 22-26 de septiembre de 1999, Consejería de Cultura del Gobierno de Cantabria, Santander, 1105–1125.

Lorenzo Gradín, P. (2003a), “Géneros y rúbricas en los cancioneros gallego- portugueses”, in Homenaje a Luís Quirante. Vol. II: Estudios filológicos, Facultat de Filologia - Universitat de València, Valencia, 625–636.

Lorenzo Gradín, P. (2003b), “Las razos gallego-portuguesas”, Romania 121: 99–132.

Lorenzo Gradín, P. (2008a), “Colocci, los lais de Bretanha y las rúbricas explicativas de B y V”, in C. Bologna e M. Bernardi (eds.), Angelo Colocci e gli studi romanzi, Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, Città del Vaticano, 405–430.

Lorenzo Gradín, P. (2008b), “Hiato e sinalefa na lírica profana galego-portuguesa”, in E. Corral Díaz, L. Fontoira Surís & E. Moscoso Mato (eds.), A mi dizen quantos amigos ey: homenaxe ao profesor Xosé Luís Couceiro, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 265–272.

Lorenzo Gradín, P. (2008c), “Reflexións sobre os encontros vocálicos nas cantigas”, in M. Brea, F. Fernández Rei & X. L. Regueira Fernández (eds.), Cada palabra pesaba, cada palabra medía: homenaxe a Antón Santamarina, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 513–521.

Lorenzo Gradín, P. (2009), “Sobre el cómputo métrico en la lírica gallego-portuguesa”, in F. Brugnolo & F. Gambino (eds.), La lirica romanza del Medioevo. Storia, tradizioni, interpretazioni. Atti del VI Convegno triennale della Società Italiana di Filologia Romanza, Vol. II, Unipress, Padova, 493–508.

Lorenzo Gradín, P. (2012), “Orden y desorden en el cancionero gallego-portugués B. Las claves del texto y del libro”, The Romanic Review 102(1-2): 27–48.

Lorenzo Gradín, P. (2013), “Los lais de Bretanha: de la compilación en prosa al cancionero”, e-Spania 16 [Link].

Lowry, M. (2003), s.v. ”Colocci, Angelo, of Iesi”, in T. B. Deutscher & P. G. Bietenholz (eds.), Contemporaries of Erasmus: A Biographical Register of the Renaissance and Reformation, University of Toronto Press, Toronto. 1ast ed. 1987.

Marcenaro, S. (2012), Pero Garcia Burgalês. Canzoniere: poesie d'amore, d'amico e di scherno, Edizioni dell'Orso, Alessandria.

Marcenaro, S. (2014), “Il galego-portoghese dei canzonieri medievali. Lingua d’autore o di copista?”, Critica del testo XVII(3): 25–44.

Marcerano, V. (2018), La lingua dei trobadores, Viella, Roma [No prelo].

Monaci, E. (ed.) (1875), Il Canzoniere portoghese della Biblioteca Vaticana, Max Niemeyer, Halle a. S.

Monteagudo, H. (2008), Letras primeiras: o Foral de Caldelas, a emerxencia da escrita en galego e os primordios da lírica trobadoresca, Fundación Pedro Barrié de la Maza, A Coruña.

Monteagudo, H. (2014a), A nobreza miñota e a lírica trobadoresca na Galicia da primeira metade do século XIII: a personalidade histórica do trobador Johan Soayrez Somesso, os trobadores Afonso Soarez Sarraça e Estevan Fayan, Toxosoutos, Noia.

Monteagudo, H. (2014b), “O pergamiño Vindel”, in H. Monteagudo (ed.), Bañarnos emos nas ondas! As sete cantigas / O pergamiño Vindel, 13–21.

Monteagudo, H. (2015a), “Cuita grand’e cuidado (A32) / Coita grand’e coydado (B174). Estratigrafía da variación lingüística nos cancioneiros troabadorescos”, Boletín da Real Academia Galega 374: 209–299.

Monteagudo, H. (2015b), “Variação scriptolinguística e estratigrafia comparada de A e B: achegas à proto-tradição manuscrita dos cancioneiros galego-portugueses”, Revista Diacrítica 29(1): 472–497.

Montero Santalha, J.-M. (2000), As rimas da poesia trovadoresca galego-portuguesa: catálogo e análise, Tese de doutoramento inédita, Universidade da Coruña, A Coruña.

Montero Santalha, J.-M. (2004), “Cantigas trovadorescas (edição digital): Critérios de transcrição e de edição de textos” [Link].

Montoya Martínez, J. (2000), “Algunas precisiones acerca de la puntuación de las Cantigas de Santa María”, in S. Parkinson (ed.), Cobras e Son: papers on the text, music and manuscripts of the “Cantigas de Santa Maria”, University of Oxford, European Humanities Research Centre, Oxford, 119–132.

Nunes, J. J. (ed.) (1971), Cantigas d'amigo dos trovadores galego-portugueses, Kraus Reprint, New York.

Oliveira, A. Resende de (1994), Depois do espectáculo trovadoresco: a estrutura dos cancioneiros peninsulares e as recolhas dos séculos XIII e XIV, Colibri, Lisboa.

Oliveira, A. Resende de (1995), Trobadores e xograres: contexto histórico, Edicións Xerais de Galicia, Vigo.

Oliveira, A. Resende de (2001), O Trovador galego-português e o seu mundo, Notícias, Lisboa.

Pedro, S. Tavares (2004), “Análise paleográfica das anotações marginais e finais no Cancioneiro da Ajuda” [Link].

Pedro, S. Tavares (2017), Os sinais abreviativos no Cancioneiro da Biblioteca Nacional: tentativa de sistematização, Roma [No prelo].

Pérez Barcala, G. (2001), “Angelo Colocci y los procedimientos repetitivos en el Cancioneiro da Biblioteca Nacional de Lisboa (Cod. 10991)”, Revista de Poética Medieval 7: 53–96.

Pérez Barcala, G. (2008), “Angelo Colocci y la rima románica: aspectos estructurales (Análisis de algunas apostillas coloccianas)”, in C. Bologna & M. Bernardi (eds.), Angelo Colocci e gli studi romanzi, Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, Città del Vaticano, 315–361.

Pérez Priego, M. á. (2011), La edición de textos, 2and ed, Síntesis, Madrid.

Petrucci, F. (1982), s.v. “Colocci, Angelo”, in Dizionario Biografico degli Italiani, Vol. 27, Istituto dell'Enciclopedia Italiana, Roma, 105–111.

Ramos, M. A. (1988), “Um provençalismo no Cancioneiro da Ajuda: senner”, in D. Kremer (ed.), Homenagem a Joseph M. Piel por ocasião do seu 85 aniversário, Max Niemeyer, Tübingen, 622–637.

Ramos, M. A. (1993), s.v. “Cancioneiro da Ajuda”, in G. Lanciani & G. Tavani (eds.), Dicionário da literatura medieval galega e portuguesa, Caminho, Lisboa, 115–117.

Ramos, M. A. (1994), “Descrição do manuscrito”, in Fragmento do Nobiliario do Conde Dom Pedro. Cancioneiro da Ajuda. Edição fac-similada do códice existente na Biblioteca da Ajuda. Apresentação, estudos e índices, Távola redonda-Instituto Português do Património Arquitectónico e Arqueológico, Biblioteca da Ajuda, Lisboa, 27–47.

Ramos, M. A. (2005), “Mise en texte nos manuscritos da lírica galego-portuguesa”, in R. Alemany, J. L. Martos & J. M. Manzanaro (eds.), Actes del X Congrés Internacional de l'Associació Hispànica de Literatura Medieval, Vol. III, Institut Interuniversitari de Filologia Valenciana, Alacant, 1333–1353.

Ramos, M. A. (2008), O Cancioneiro da Ajuda. Confeccção e escrita, Tese de doutoramento inédita, Universidade de Lisboa, Lisboa.

Ramos, M. A. (2009), “La genesi di un canzoniere: copisti e dinamica testuale”, in F. Brugnolo & F. Gambino (eds.), La lirica romanza del Medioevo. Storia, tradizioni, interpretazioni. Atti del VI Convegno triennale della Società Italiana di Filologia Romanza, Vol. II, Unipress, Padova, 473–492.

Ramos, M. A. (2011), ““Sombras” grafemáticas. Dimensão diacrónica na formação dos cancioneiros galego-portugueses”, in La tradizione della lirica nel medioevo romanzo. Problemi di filologia formale, Edizioni del Galuzzo per la Fondazione Ezio Franceschini, Firenze, 333–361.

Río Riande, M. G. del (2010), Texto y contexto: el Cancionero del rey don Denis de Portugal (edición crítica y estudio filológico).

Rio Riande, M. G. del (2011a), “La transmisión material de la lírica profana gallego-portuguesa: contribución a la descripción codicológica y paleográfica del Manuscrito o Fragmento de Torre do Tombo o Pergamino Sharrer (T)”, in M. Salamanca López (ed.), La materialidad escrita: Nuevos enfoques para su interpretación, Instituto de Estudios para la Paz y la Cooperación, Oviedo, 187–229.

Río Riande, M. G. del (2011b), “Rótulos y follas: las rúbricas del Cancioneiro del rey Don Denis”, in M. Arbor Aldea & A. Fernández Guiadanes (eds.), Estudos de edición crítica e lírica galego-portuguesa, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 195–223.

Rodríguez Guerra, A. (1993), “Contributos para a análise material e paleográfica do Fragmento Sharrer”, in A. A. Nascimento & C. Almeida Ribeiro (eds.), Actas do IV Congresso da Associação Hispânica de Literatura Medieval (Lisboa, 1-5 Outubro 1991), Cosmos, Lisboa, 31–33.

Rodríguez Guerra, A. & Varela Barreiro, F. X. (2007), “As grafías no Cancioneiro da Ajuda”, in A. I. Boullón Agrelo (ed.), Na nosa lyngoage galega: a emerxencia do galego como lingua escrita na Idade Media, Consello da Cultura Galega-Instituto da Lingua Galega, Santiago de Compostela, 473–556 [Link].

Sharrer, H. L. (1993), “Fragmentos de sete cantigas d’amor de D. Dinis, musicadas: uma descoberta”, in Actas do Congresso da Associação Hispânica de Literatura Medieval, Vol. I, Cosmos, Lisboa, 13–29.

Sharrer, H. L. (2004), “Estado actual de los estudios sobre el Cancioneiro da Ajuda”, in O Cancioneiro da Ajuda cen anos despois: actas do Congreso realizado pola Dirección Xeral de Promoción Cultural en Santiago de Compostela e na Illa de San Simón os días 25-28 de maio de 2004, Consellería de Cultura, Comunicación Social e Turismo, Santiago de Compostela, 41–54.

Souto Cabo, J. A. (2008b), “O texto das cantigas no quadro das prácticas escriturais do séc. XIII”, in M. Ferreiro, C. P. Martínez Pereiro & L. Tato Fontaíña (eds.), A edición da poesía trobadoresca en Galiza, Baía, A Coruña, 161–176.

Souto Cabo, J. A. (2011), “A emergência da lírica galego-portuguesa e os primeiros trovadores”, A Trabe de ouro 87(3): 367–392.

Souto Cabo, J. A. (2012), Os cavaleiros que fizeram as cantigas: aproximação às origens socioculturais da lírica galego-portuguesa, Editora da Universidade Federal Fluminense, Niterói.

Stuart de Rothesay, C. (1823), Fragmentos de hum Cancioneiro inedito, que se acha na livraria do Real Collegio dos Nobres de Lisboa, Tipografia da Embaixada Britânica, Paris.

Varela Barreiro, F. X. (2005), “Os usos das letras maiúsculas no Cancioneiro da Ajuda”, in A. I. Boullón Agrelo, X. L. Couceiro & F. Fernández Rei (eds.), As tebras alumeadas: estudos filolóxicos ofrecidos en homenaxe a Ramón Lorenzo, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela, Servizo de Publicacións e Intercambio Científico, Santiago de Compostela, 275–288.

Varela Barreiro, F. X. & Mariño Paz, R. (2005), “O uso dos signos gráficos <u>, <V> e <U> no Cancioneiro da Ajuda”, in M. Brea (ed.), Carolina Michaëlis e o Cancioneiro da Ajuda, hoxe, Xunta de Galicia, Dirección Xeral de Política Lingüística / Centro Ramón Piñeiro para a Investigación en Humanidades, Santiago de Compostela, 309–374.

Vasconcelos, C. Michaëlis de (ed.) (1904), Cancioneiro da Ajuda, Max Niemeyer, Halle a S.

Vieira, Y. Frateschi (1999), “En cas dona Maior”: os trovadores e a corte senhorial galega no século XIII, Laiovento, Santiago de Compostela.

Vieira, Y. Frateschi (2012), “Os Lais de Bretanha: voltando à questão da autoria”, in L. M. Mongelli (ed.), E Fizerom taes Maravilhas... Histórias de Cavaleiros e Cavalarias, Atelie Editorial, 527–544.

↑

Crítica textual e Humanidades DixitaisCrítica textual e Humanidades DigitaisTextual scholarship and Digital Humanities

Alvarado, R. C. (2012), “The Digital Humanities Situation”, in M. K. Gold (ed.), Debates in the digital humanities, Univ. of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis, 50–55.

Andrews, T. L. (2014), “Digital Techniques for Critical Edition”, in V. Calzolari (ed.), Armenian Philology in the Modern Era: From Manuscript to Digital Text, BRILL, Leiden-Boston, 175–195.

Andrews, T. L. & Mace, C. (2013), “Beyond the tree of texts: Building an empirical model of scribal variation through graph analysis of texts and stemmata”, Literary and Linguistic Computing 28(4): 504–521 [Link].

Balduino, A. (1979), Manuale di filologia italiana, Sansoni, Firenze.

Bański, P. (2010), “Why TEI stand-off annotation doesn't quite work: and why you might want to use it nevertheless”, in Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2010, Vol. 5, Balisage Series on Markup Technologies.

Bédier, J. (1922), La Chanson de Roland; publiée d'après le manuscrit d'Oxford et traduite par Joseph Bédier, L'Edition d'art, H. Piazza, Paris.

Bellemin-Noël, J. & Milosz, O. V. d. L. (1972), Le texte et l'avant-texte: les brouillons d'un poème de Milosz, Larousse, Paris.

Bermúdez Sabel, H. (2017), “Colación asistida por ordenador: estado de la cuestión y retos”, Revista de Humanidades Digitales 1: 20–34 [Link].

Bermúdez Sabel, H. (2019), “Anotación multicamada externa e o enriquecemento de edicións dixitais”, in D. González & H. Bermúdez Sabel (eds.), Humanidades Digitales. Miradas hacia la Edad Media, De Gruyter, Berlin, 4–17 [Link].

Berry, D. M. (2012), “Introduction: Understanding the Digital Humanities”, in D. M. Berry (ed.), Understanding digital humanities, Palgrave Macmillan, Basingstoke / New York, 1–20.

Birnbaum, D. J. (2011), “What is XML and why should humanists care? An even gentler introduction to XML” [Link].

Blecua, A. (1983), Manual de crítica textual, Castalia, Madrid.

Bleier, R. (2016), “Report: Digital Scholarly Editions as Interfaces Symposium”. [Link].

Brea, M. (1985), “Las preposiciones, del latín a las lenguas románicas”, Verba 12: 147–182.

Bryant, J. (2002), The Fluid Text: A Theory of Revision and Editing for Book and Screen, University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor.

Canet, J. L. (2014), “Reflexiones sobre las humanidades digitales”, in S. López Poza & N. Pena Sueiro (eds.), Humanidades Digitales: desafíos, logros y perspectivas de futuro, SIELAE, A Coruña, 11–20 [Link].

Cerquiglini, B. (1989), Éloge de la variante: Histoire critique de la philologie, éditions du Seuil.

Chiesa, P. (2002), Elementi di critica testuale, Pàtron Editore, Bologna.

Colwell, E. C. & Tune, E. W. (1964), “Variant Readings: Classification and Use”, Journal of Biblical Literature 83(3): 253–261.

Contini, G. (1953), Racconti della scapigliatura piemontese, Bompiani, Milano.

Cummings, J. (2007), “The Text Encoding Initiative and the Study of Literature”, in R. G. Siemens & S. Schreibman (eds.), A companion to digital literary studies, Blackwell Pub., Malden, MA, 451–476.

D’Agostino, A. (2006), Capitoli di Filologia testuale. Testi italiani e romanzi, 2and ed, CUEM, Gorgonzola-Milano.

Dain, M.-A. (1964), Les manuscrits, 2and ed, Société d’édition «Les Belles Lettres», Paris [1ast ed. 1949].

Dekker, R. H. & Birnbaum, D. J. (2017), “It's more than just overlap: Text As Graph”, in Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2017, Vol. 19, Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, Washington, DC [Link].

Dekker, R. H. & Middell, G. (2011), “Computer-Supported Collation with CollateX: Managing Textual Variance in an Environment with Varying Requirements”, in Supporting Digital Humanities, University of Copenhagen, Denmark [Link]

Dekker, R. H., van Hulle, D., Middell, G., Neyt, V. & van Zundert, J. (2015), “Computer-supported collation of modern manuscripts: CollateX and the Beckett Digital Manuscript Project”, Digital Scholarship in the Humanities 30(3): 452–470 [Link].

Driscoll, M. J. (2006), “Levels of transcription”, in L. Burnard, K. O'Brien O'Keeffe & J. Unsworth (eds.), Electronic Textual Editing, Modern Language Association of America, New York, 254–261.

Drucker, J. (2012), “Humanistic Theory and Digital Scholarship”, in M. K. Gold (ed.), Debates in the digital humanities, Univ. of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis, 85–95.

Emiliano, A. (2002), “Problemas de transliteração na edição de textos medievais”, Revista galega de filoloxía 3: 29–64.

Epp, E. J. (2007), “It's All about Variants: A Variant-Conscious Approach to New Testament Textual Criticism”, The Harvard Theological Review 100(3): 275–308.

Faulhaber, C. B. & Marcos Marín, F. (1992), “La conservación y utilización de textos en el futuro inmediato: ADMYTE, el archivo digital de manuscritos y textos españoles”, Hispania 75(4): 1010–1023.

Fitzpatrick, K. (2012), “The Humanities, Done Digitally”, in M. K. Gold (ed.), Debates in the digital humanities, Univ. of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis, 12–15.

Flanders, J. (2011), “Collaboration and Dissent: Challenges of Collaborative Standards for Digital Humanities”, in M. Deegan & W. McCarty (eds.), Collaborative research in the digital humanities, Ashgate Pub., Farnham, 67–80.

Fradejas Rueda, J. M. (2009), “La codificación XML/TEI de textos medievales”, Memorabilia 12: 219–247. 00000 [Link].

Fränkel, H. (1969), Testo critico e critica del texto, Le Monnier, Firenze.

Gabler, H. W. (2010), “Theorizing the digital scholarly edition”, Literature Compass 7(2): 43–56 [Link].

Haugen, O. E. (2014), “The making of an edition: three crucial dimensions”, in Digital critical editions, Topics in the digital humanities, University of Illinois Press, Urbana, 203–245.

Hockey, S. (2004), “The history of Humanities Computing”, in S. Schreibman, R. G. Siemens & J. Unsworth (eds.), A companion to digital humanities, Blackwell Pub., Malden, Mass., 3–19.

Hockey, S. (2011), “Digital Humanities in the Age of the Internet: Reaching Out to Other Communities”, in M. Deegan & W. McCarty (eds.), Collaborative research in the digital humanities, Ashgate, Farnham, 81–92.

Hockey, S. M. (2000), Electronic texts in the humanities: principles and practice, Oxford University Press, Oxford-New York.

Ide, N. & Romary, L. (2004), “International standard for a linguistic annotation framework”, Natural Language Engineering 10(3-4): 211–225.

Interedition Development Group (2017), “CollateX” [Link]

Italia, P., Vitali, F. & Di Iorio, A. (2015), “Variants and Versioning Between Textual Bibliography and Computer Science”, in Proceedings of the Third AIUCD Annual Conference on Humanities and Their Methods in the Digital Ecosystem, AIUCD '14, ACM, New York, NY, USA, 2:1–2:5 [Link].

Jockers, M. L. (2013), Macroanalysis: Digital Methods & Literary History, University of Illinois Press, Illinois. bibtex: JockersMacroanalysisDigitalMethods2013.

Kelly, A. (2015), “Tablet computers for the dissemination of digital scholarly editions”, Manuscrítica 28: 123–140.

Kestemont, M. (2012), “Stylometry for Medieval Authorship Studies: An Application to Rhyme Words”, Digital Philology: A Journal of Medieval Cultures 1(1): 42–72 [Link].

Kline, M.-J. (1998), A Guide to Documentary Editing, Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore.

Lin, Y.-w. (2012), “Transdisciplinary and Digital humanities: Lessons Learned from Developing Text-Mining Tools for Textual Analysis”, in D. M. Berry (ed.), Understanding digital humanities, Palgrave Macmillan, Basingstoke / New York, 295–314.

Liu, A. (2013), “From Reading to Social Computing”, in K. M. Price & R. Siemens (eds.), Literary Studies in the Digital Age, Modern Language Association of America, New York [Link].

Lucía Megías, J. M. (1998), “Editar en Internet (che quanto piace il mondo è breve sogno)”, Incipit 18: 1–40.

Lucía Megías, J. M. (2003), “La informática humanística: notas volanderas desde el ámbito hispánico”, Incipit 23: 91–114.

Lucía Megías, J. M. (2007), “La edición crítica hipertextual: la superación del incunable del hipertexto”, in Lecturas y textos en el siglo XXI: nuevos caminos en la edición textual, Universidad de Jaén, Jaén [Link].

Lucía Megías, J. M. (2012), Elogio del texto digital. Claves para interpretar el nuevo paradigma, Fórcola, Madrid.

Lucía Megías, J. M. (2014), “Las Humanidades Digitales: una oportunidad para los hispanistas del siglo XXI”, in á. Baraibar (ed.), Humanidades digitales: una aproximación transdisciplinar, SIELAE, A Coruña, 99–116. [Link].

Maas, P. J. M. (1927), Textkritik, Teubner, Leipzig.

McCarty, W. (2005), Humanities computing, Palgrave Macmillan, Basingstoke / New York.

Middell, G. (2011), “Textual Variance” [Link].

Mink, G. (2000), “Editing and genealogical studies: the New Testament”, Literary and Linguistic Computing 15(1): 51–56 [Link].

Moretti, F. (2013), Distant reading, Verso, London-New York.

Nassourou, M. (2013), Computer-Supported Textual Criticism: Theory, Automatic Reconstruction of an Archetype, BoD – Books on Demand.

Orduna, G. (1986), “Un nuevo tipo de edición: «la edición sinóptica experimental»”, Incipit VI: 103–105.

Orduna, G. (2000), Ecdótica: problemática de la edición de textos, Reichenberger, Kassel.

Orlandi, T. (2010), Informatica testuale. Teoria e prassi, Laterza, Bari.

Ostrowski, D., Birnbaum, D. J. & Lunt, H. G. (eds.) (2004), Texts: The Povest' vremennykh let: An Interlinear Collation and Paradosis, Harvard Ukrainian Research Institute, Cambridge (Mass.).

Parkinson, S. R. & Emiliano, A. (2002), “Encoding Medieval Abbreviations for Computer Analysis (from Latin-Portuguese and Portuguese Non-literary Sources)”, Literary and Linguistic Computing 17(3): 345–360 [Link].

Pérez Priego, M. á. (2011), La edición de textos, 2and ed, Síntesis, Madrid.

Performant Software Solutions LLC (2014), “Juxta” [Link].

Pierazzo, E. (2015), Digital scholarly editing: theories, models and methods, Ashgate, Farnham.

Piez, W. (2008), “Something Called Digital Humanities”, Digital Humanities Quarterly 2(1) [Link].

Piez, W. (2014), “Hierarchies within range space: From LMNL to OHCO”, in Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2014, Vol. 13, Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, Washington, DC [Link]

Pose, J., Lopez, P. & Romary, L. (2014), “A Generic Formalism for Encoding Stand-off annotations in TEI” [Link]

Priani Saisó, E., Spence, P., Galina Russell, I., González-Blanco García, E., Alves, D., Barrón Tovar, J. F., Godínez Bustos, M. A. & Paixão de Sousa, M. C. (2014), “Las humanidades digitales en español y portugués. Un estudio de caso: DíaHD/DiaHD”, Anuario Americanista Europeo 12: 5–18.

Price, K. M. (2007), “Electronic Scholarly Editions”, in R. G. Siemens e S. Schreibman (eds.), A companion to digital literary studies, Blackwell Pub., Malden, MA, 434–450.

Ramsay, S. (2011), Reading machines toward an algorithmic criticism, University of Illinois Press, Urbana.

Ramsay, S. (2014), “The Hermeneutics of Screwing Around; or What You Do with a Million Books”, in K. Kee (ed.), Pastplay: Teaching and Learning History with Technology, University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 111–120.

Renear, A. H. (2004), “Text Encoding”, in S. Schreibman, R. G. Siemens e J. Unsworth (eds.), A companion to digital humanities, Blackwell Pub., Malden, Mass., 218–239.

Renear, A., Mylonas, E. & Durand, D. (1993), “Refining our Notion of What Text Really Is: The Problem of Overlapping Hierarchies”, Center for Digital Scholarship, Boston [Link].

Rojas Castro, A. (2013), “El mapa y el territorio. Una aproximación histórico-bibliográfica a la emergencia de las Humanidades Digitales en España”, Caracteres 2(2): 10–53 [Link].

Romary, L. (2015), “Standards for language resources in ISO – Looking back at 13 fruitful years”, edition - die Terminologiefachzeitschrift 15(2): 13–19 [Link].

Roncaglia, A. (1975), Principi e applicazioni di critica testuale, Bulzoni, Roma.

Roudil, J. (ed.) (1986), Oeuvres, Klincksieck, Paris.

Ruiz, E. (1985), “Crítica textual. Edición de textos”, in J. M. Díaz Borque (ed.), Métodos de estudio de la obra literaria, Taurus, Madrid, 67–120.

Ruiz, E. (2002), Introducción a la codicología, Fundación Germán Sánchez Ruiperez, Madrid. 1ast ed. 1988.

Rychner, J. (1958), Le lai de Lanval. Texte critique et édition diplomatique des quatre manuscrits français par Jean Rychner. Accompagné du texte du “Ianuals ljod” et de sa traduction française, Droz, Genève.

Sánchez-Prieto Borja, P. (1998), Cómo editar los textos medievales. Criterios para su presentación gráfica, Arco Libros, Madrid.

Santamarina, A. (1974a), “Contribución pra un estudio das partículas comparativas que = ca e como = coma en galego”, Verba 1: 16–30.

Schmidt, D. & Colomb, R. (2009), “A data structure for representing multi-version texts online”, International Journal of Human-Computer Studies 67(6): 497–514.

Segre, C. (1979), Semiotica filologica, Einaudi.

Shillingsburg, P. L. (1996), Scholarly Editing in the Computer Age: Theory and Practice, University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor.

Shillingsburg, P. L. (2006), From Gutenberg to Google: electronic representations of literary texts, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK-New York.

Spence, P. (2014a), “Centros y fronteras: el panorama internacional”, in S. López Poza & N. Pena Sueiro (eds.), Humanidades Digitales: desafíos, logros y perspectivas de futuro, SIELAE, A Coruña, 37–61 [Link].

Spence, P. (2014b), “La investigación humanística en la era digital: mundo académico y nuevos espacios”, in á. Baraibar (ed.), Humanidades digitales: una aproximación transdisciplinar, SIELAE, A Coruña, 117–131 [Link].

Spencer, M. & Howe, C. (2004), “Collating Texts Using Progressive Multiple Alignment”, Computers and the Humanities 38(3): 253–270.

Spiro, L. (2012), “This Is Why We Fight: Defining the Values of the Digital Humanities”, in M. K. Gold (ed.), Debates in the digital humanities, Univ. of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis, 16–35.

Stussi, A. (1994), Introduzione agli studi di filologia italiana, il Mulino, Bologna.

Taavitsainen, I. & Pahta, P. (n.d.), “Placing the Helsinki Corpus Middle English Section Introduction into Context” [Link].

Tanselle, G. T. (2006), “Foreword”, in Electronic Textual Editing, Modern Language Association of America, New York, 3–7.

TEI Consortium (2014), “TEI: History” [Link].

TEI Consortium (2016a), “The Double End-Point Attachment Method”, in TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange. Version 3.1.0. Last updated on 15th December 2016 [Link].

TEI Consortium (2016b), “Feature Structures”, in P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange. Version 3.1.0. Last updated on 15th December 2016 [Link].

TEI Consortium (2016c), “A Gentle Introduction to XML”, in TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange [Link].

TEI Consortium (2016d), “The Parallel Segmentation Method”, in TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange. Version 3.1.0. Last updated on 15th December 2016 [Link].

Terras, M. M., Nyhan, J. & Vanhoutte, E. (2013), “Selected Definitions from the Day of Digital Humanities 2009–2012”, in Defining digital humanities: a reader, Ashgate, Farnham, 279–288.

Timpanaro, S. (1963), La genesi del metodo del Lachmann, Le Monnier, Firenze.

Trovato, P. (2014), Everything You Always Wanted to Know about Lachmann’s Method. A Non-Standard Handbook of Genealogical Textual Criticism in the Age of Post-Structuralism, Cladistics, and Copy-Text, libreriauniversitaria.it, Padova.

Unsworth, J. (2000), “Scholarly Primitives: what methods do humanities researchers have in common, and how might our tools reflect this?” [Link].

Unsworth, J. (2013), “What is Humanities Computing and What is Not?”, in M. Terras, E. Vanhoutte & J. Nyhan (eds.), Defining Digital Humanities: a Reader, Ashgate, Farnham, 35–48.

Vanhoutte, E. (2013), “The Gates of Hell. History and Definition of Digital | Humanities | Computing”, in M. M. Terras, J. Nyhan & E. Vanhoutte (eds.), Defining digital humanities: a reader, Ashgate, Farnham, 119–156.

Weis, R. (2009), King Lear: Parallel Text Edition, 2and ed, Routledge, Harlow [1ast ed. 1993].

Witt, A. & Stegmann, J. (2009), “TEI Feature Structures as a Representation Format for Multiple Annotation and Generic XML Documents”, in Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2009, Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, Montréal, Canada [Link].

↑